This man is wearing what we call
هذا الرجل يضع ما نسميه
a bee beard. (Laughter)
لحية النحل (ضحك)
A beard full of bees.
لحية مملوءة بالنحل
Now, this is what many of you might picture
الآن ، هذا ماقد يتصوره الكثير منكم
when you think about honeybees, maybe insects,
عندما يفكر في نحل العسل ، ربما حشرات،
or maybe anything that has more legs than two.
آو ربما أي شيء لديه أرجل زيادة على اثنتين
And let me start by telling you, I gotcha.
ودعني أبدأ بإخباركم، أمسكت بكم.
I understand that. But, there are many things to know,
أتفهم ذلك. ولكن هناك العديد من الأشياء لنعرفها
and I want you to open your minds here,
وأريدكم أن تفتحوا عقولكم هنا
keep them open, and change your perspective about honeybees.
إبقوها مفتوحة، وغيروا نظرتكم لنحل العسل
Notice that this man is not getting stung.
لاحظوا أن هذا الرجل لم يُلسع
He probably has a queen bee tied to his chin,
من المحتمل أن يكون لديه ملكة نحل معلقة في ذقنه
and the other bees are attracted to it.
وباقي النحل منجذب لها
So this really demonstrates our relationship with honeybees,
هذا بالفعل يمثل علاقتنا بنحل العسل
and that goes deep back for thousands of years.
وهذا يرجع قديماً إلى آلاف السنين
We're very co-evolved, because we depend on bees
إننا مشتركون جداّ في التطور، لأننا نعتمد على النحل
for pollination and, even more recently,
من أجل التلقيح وبشكل أكثر حتى مؤخراً
as an economic commodity.
كسلعة اقتصادية
Many of you may have heard that honeybees are disappearing,
معظمكم قد سمع أن نحل العسل على وشك الانقراض
not just dying, but they're gone.
ليس فقط بالموت، ولكنه اختفى
We don't even find dead bodies.
حتى أننا لا نعثر على جثث
This is called colony collapse disorder,
هذا ما يطلق عليه خلل انهيار المستعمرة
and it's bizarre. Researchers around the globe
وهذا غريب، فما يزال الباحثون حول العالم
still do not know what's causing it,
لا يعلمون ما السبب وراء ذلك
but what we do know is that, with the declining numbers
ولكن ما نعلمه هو أنه، ومع تراجع أرقام النحل
of bees, the costs of over 130 fruit and vegetable crops
فإن تكلفة محاصيل أكثر من 130 صنف من الفاكهة والخضروات
that we rely on for food is going up in price.
التي نعتمد عليها في غذائنا آخذة في الارتفاع
So honeybees are important for their role in the economy
إذن فإن نحل العسل مهم جدا لدوره في الاقتصاد
as well as in agriculture.
تماماً كما في الزراعة.
Here you can see some pictures of what are called
وإليكم بعض الصور عما يسمى
green roofs, or urban agriculture.
الأسطح الخضراء ، أو زراعة المناطق الحضرية
We're familiar with the image on the left that shows
نحن معتادون على الصورة في اليسار والتي تظهر
a local neighborhood garden in the South End.
حديقة في الحي المحلي في نهاية الحي
That's where I call home. I have a beehive in the backyard.
فيما أسميه البيت. لدي خلية نحل في الساحة الخلفية
And perhaps a green roof in the future,
وربما سطح أخضر في المستقبل
when we're further utilizing urban areas,
عندما نقوم باستغلال مساحات حضرية أكثر
where there are stacks of garden spaces.
حيث توجد مجموعة من المساحات الخضراء
Check out this image above the orange line in Boston.
لاحظوا هذه الصورة أعلى الخط البرتقالي في بوسطن
Try to spot the beehive. It's there.
حاولوا العثور على الخلية. إنها هناك.
It's on the rooftop, right on the corner there,
إنها على قمة السطح، تماماً عند الركن هناك
and it's been there for a couple of years now.
وهي موجودة هناك لعدة أعوام.
The way that urban beekeeping currently operates
والطريقة التي يتم بها الحفاظ على خلايا النحل الحضرية حالياً
is that the beehives are quite hidden,
هي أن الخلايا تكاد تكون مخفية
and it's not because they need to be.
وهي ليست كذلك لأنها تحتاج أن تكون كذلك.
It's just because people are uncomfortable with the idea,
وهذا فقط لأن الناس غير مرتاحون للفكرة،
and that's why I want you today to try to think about this,
ولذلك أريدكم اليوم أن تحاولوا التفكير في هذا
think about the benefits of bees in cities
فكروا في فوائد وجود النحل في المدن
and why they really are a terrific thing.
ولماذا يعتبر شيء رائعاً
Let me give you a brief rundown on how pollination works.
دعوني أقدم لكم ملخصاً عن كيفية عمل التلقيح
So we know flowers, we know fruits and vegetables,
نحن نعرف الأزهار ، ونعرف الفواكه والخضروات
even some alfalfa in hay that the livestock
حتى بعض فصفصة النباتات في التبن التي تأكله الماشية
for the meats that we eat, rely on pollinators,
التي نأكل لحومها تعتمد على الملقحات
but you've got male and female parts to a plant here,
ولكنكم تجدون أجزاء ذكرية وأنثوية في النبات هنا،
and basically pollinators are attracted to plants
وأساسًا فإن الملقحين ينجذبون إلى النباتات
for their nectar, and in the process,
من أجل الرحيق ، وخلال هذه العملية ،
a bee will visit some flowers and pick up some pollen,
فإن النحل سيحط على بعض الأزهار ويلتقط بعض حبوب اللقاح
or that male kind of sperm counterpart, along the way,
أو ذلك النوع من الحيوانات المنوية الموجود في نظيره من الحيوانات ، على طول الطريق
and then travel to different flowers, and eventually
ومن ثم يسافر إلى أزهار مختلفة ، وأخيراً
an apple, in this case, will be produced.
سيتم إنتاج تفاحة في حالتنا هذه
You can see the orientation. The stem is down.
يمكنك معرفة التوجيه . الساق في الأسفل
The blossom end has fallen off by the time we eat it,
وتتساقط طرف الزهرة عندما نأكلها
but that's a basic overview of how pollination works.
ولكن بنظرة أساسية إلى كيفية عمل التلقيح
And let's think about urban living, not today,
ودعونا نفكر في حياة الحضر ، ليس اليوم
and not in the past, but what about in a hundred years?
وليس في الماضي ، ولكن ماذا عن المائة عام القادمة ؟
What's it gonna look like? We have huge grand challenges
ما الذي ستكون عليه ؟ لدينا تحديات ضخمة
these days of habitat loss. We have more and more people,
في أيام فقدان الموطن هذه، لدينا الكثير والكثير من الناس
billions of people, in 100 years, God knows how many people,
ملايير البشر ، خلال 100 عام ، الله أعلم كم عدد البشر
and how little space there will be to fit all of them,
وما ضيق المساحة المتوفرة لكل هؤلاء
so we need to change the way that we see cities, and
لذلك فإنه علينا أن نغير الطريقة التي نرى بها المدن
looking at this picture on the left of New York City today,
وبالنظر إلى هذه الصورة في اليسار من مدينة نيويورك اليوم
you can see how gray and brown it is.
يمكنكم مشاهدة الألوان الرمادية والبنية فيها
We have tar paper on the rooftops that bounces heat back
لدينا رقاقات القطران على أسطح العمارات التي تعكس الحرارة
into the atmosphere,
في الغلاف الجوي
contributing to global climate change, no doubt.
بدون شك مساهمة في تغير المناخ العالمي
What about in 100 years, if we have green rooftops
ماذا عن 100 عام ، لو كانت لدينا أسطح خضراء
everywhere, and gardening, and we create our own crops
في كل مكان ، وبستنة ، وزراعة محاصيلنا الخاصة بنا
right in the cities? We save on the costs of transportation,
في المدن ؟ سنوفر تكلفة النقل
we save on a healthier diet, and we also educate
سنوفر بنظام غذائي صحي أكثر ،
and create new jobs locally.
وسنتعلم أيضاَ و نخلق فرص عمل محلية .
We need bees for the future of our cities and urban living.
نحن نحتاج النحل لمستقبل مدننا وحياتنا الحضرية.
Here's some data that we collected through our company
إليكم بعض البيانات التي جمعناها من خلال شركتنا
with Best Bees, where we deliver, install and manage
مع Best Bees ، حيث نوصل، ونركب وندير
honeybee hives for anybody who wants them,
خلايا النحل لأي شخص يريدها
in the city, in the countryside, and we introduce honeybees,
في المدينة ، في الريف ، كما نقدم نحل العسل،
and the idea of beekeeping in your own backyard or rooftop
وفكرة الحفاظ على النحل في ساحاتكم الخلفية أو على الأسطح
or fire escape, for even that matter,
أو مخارج الحريق ، من أجل ذلك
and seeing how simple it is and how possible it is.
ومشاهدة مدى سهولة ذلك، وإمكانية تنفيذه.
There's a counterintuitive trend that we noticed
هناك حدس موجه لاحظناه
in these numbers. So let's look at the first metric here,
في هذه الأرقام . لذا دعونا ننظر إلى أول الأرقام هنا،
overwintering survival.
الناجون من البيات الشتوي
Now this has been a huge problem for many years,
كانت هذه مشكلة كبيرة لأعوام عديدة،
basically since the late 1980s, when the varroa mite came
أساساً منذ الثمانينات ، عندما ظهر سوس الفارروا
and brought many different viruses, bacteria
وأحضر العديد من الفيروسات والبكتيريا
and fungal diseases with it.
والأمراض الفطرية معه.
Overwintering success is hard,
كان نجاح البيات الشتوي صعباً
and that's when most of the colonies are lost,
وذلك عندما فقدنا معظم المستعمرات
and we found that in the cities, bees are surviving
ووجدنا أنه في المدن ، فقد نجا النحل
better than they are in the country.
أفضل مما لو كانوا في الريف
A bit counterintuitive, right?
قليل من الحدس ، حقاً ؟
We think, oh, bees, countryside, agriculture,
نحن نعتقد أن النحل ينتمي إلى الريف والزراعة
but that's not what the bees are showing.
ولكن هذا ليس ما يظهره النحل.
The bees like it in the city. (Laughter)
النحل يحب المدن. (ضحك)
Furthermore, they also produce more honey.
علاوة على ذلك ، فإنهم ينتجون عسلاًّ أكثر
The urban honey is delicious.
العسل الحضري لذيذ
The bees in Boston on the rooftop of the Seaport Hotel,
النحل في بوسطن على أسطح فندق سي بورت
where we have hundreds of thousands of bees
حيث لدينا مئات الآلاف من النحل
flying overheard right now
يطيرون فوقنا الآن
that I'm sure none of you noticed when we walked by,
وإنني متأكد أن لا أحد منكم لاحظ ذلك عندما كنا نسير بجوارها
are going to all of the local community gardens
سوف يذهبون إلى كل حدائق المجتمع المحلي
and making delicious, healthy honey
ويصنعون عسلاً صحياً ولذيذاً
that just tastes like the flowers in our city.
بطعم يشبه تماماً الأزهار في مدينتنا
So the yield for urban hives, in terms of honey production,
لذا فإن العائد من الخلايا الحضرية ، بالنسبة لانتاج العسل
is higher as well as the overwintering survival,
هو أكثر فضلاً عن العيش خلال البيات الشتوي
compared to rural areas.
بالمقارنة مع المناطق الريفية
Again, a bit counterintuitive.
أيضاً ، بحدس بسيط
And looking back historically at the timeline
وبنظرة تاريخية في تاريخ صحة
of honeybee health, we can go back to the year 950 and see
نحل العسل ، يمكننا الرجوع إلى الوراء الى عام 950 ونرى
that there was also a great mortality of bees in Ireland.
أنه كان هناك ايضاً معدل وفيات في النحل في أيرلندا
So the problems of bees today isn't necessarily
إذن فمشكلة النحل اليوم ليست بالضرورة شيئاً حديثاً .
something new. It has been happening
فقد حدثت
since over a thousand years ago,
منذ حوالي ألف سنة
but what we don't really notice are these problems in cities.
ولكن ما لم نلاحظه بالفعل هي تلك المشاكل في المدن
So one thing I want to encourage you to think about
لذلك فلدي شيء واحد أود تشجيعكم على التفكير فيه
is the idea of what an urban island is.
هو فكرة ماهية الجزيرة الحضرية
You think in the city maybe the temperature's warmer.
تعتقدون أنه في المدينة من المحتمل أن تكون درجة الحرارة أكثر دفئاً
Why are bees doing better in the city?
لماذا يقوم النحل بعمله أفضل في المدينة ؟
This is a big question now to help us understand
هذا سؤال كبير الآن سيساعدنا لفهم
why they should be in the city.
لماذا يجب أن يكونوا في المدينة
Perhaps there's more pollen in the city.
احتمال وجود حبوب لقاح أكثر في المدينة
With the trains coming in to urban hubs, they can
مع قدوم القطارات إلى الحلقات الحضرية ، يمكنها
carry pollen with them, very light pollen,
حمل حبوب اللقاح معها ، الحبوب الخفيفة جداً
and it's just a big supermarket in the city.
وأنه يوجد سوق كبير في المدينة
A lot of linden trees live along the railroad tracks.
والكثير من أشجار الزيزفون عبر مسارات السكة الحديدية
Perhaps there are fewer pesticides in the cities
احتمال وجود مبيدات حشرية أقل في المدن
than there are in [rural] areas.
عنها في المساحات الريفية
Perhaps there are other things that we're just not thinking about yet,
احتمال وجود أشياء أخرى لم نفكر بها بعد
but that's one idea to think about, urban islands.
ولكن تلك فكرة واحدة لاعتناقها وهي الجزر الحضرية
And colony collapse disorder is not the only thing
واضطراب انهيار المستعمرة ليست هي الشيء الوحيد
affecting honeybees. Honeybees are dying,
التي تؤثر في نحل العسل. نحل العسل يحتضر
and it's a huge, huge grand challenge of our time.
وهذا تحد هائل يواجهنا في عصرنا هذا
What you can see up here is a map of the world,
ما ترونه في الأعلى هنا هو خريطة للعالم
and we're tracking the spread of this varroa mite.
ونحن نتتبع انتشار سوسة الفارروا
Now, the varroa mite is what changed the game
الآن ، سوسة الفارروا هي من يغير اللعبة
in beekeeping, and you can see, at the top right,
عند تربية النحل ، يمكنكم مشاهدة في أعلى اليمين
the years are changing, we're coming up to modern times,
سنوات التغيير ، نتحرك تجاه العصر الحديث
and you can see the spread of the varroa mite
ويمكنك رؤية مدى انتشار سوسة الفارروا
from the early 1900s through now.
منذ 1900 حتى الآن
It's 1968, and we're pretty much covering Asia.
في 1968 ، حيث نغطي قارة آسيا
1971, we saw it spread to Europe and South America,
1971 ، نراها تنتشر إلى أوروبا وجنوب أمريكا
and then, when we get to the 1980s,
وهنا ، عندما نصل إلى 1980
and specifically to 1987, the varroa mite finally came
وخاصة في 1987 ، فقد جاءت سوسة الفارروا أخيرا
to North America and to the United States,
إلى شمال أمريكا و إلى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
and that is when the game changed
وذلك عندما تغيرت قواعد اللعبة
for honeybees in the United States.
بالنسبة لعسل النحل في الولايات المتحدة
Many of us will remember our childhood growing up,
الكثير منا سيتذكر طفولتنا أثناء النمو
maybe you got stung by a bee, you saw bees on flowers.
احتمال تكون قد أصبت بلسعة من نحلة ، ترى نحلاً على الأزهار
Think of the kids today. Their childhood's a bit different.
بالنظر إلى الأطفال اليوم ، فطفولتهم مختلفة بعض الشيء
They don't experience this.
وهم لا يواجهون ذلك
The bees just aren't around anymore.
لم يعد النحل حولنا بعد الآن
So we need bees and they're disappearing and it's a big problem.
لذا نحن نحتاج إلى النحل وهي تختفي وهذه مشكلة كبيرة
What can we do here?
ما الذي يمكننا فعله هنا ؟
So, what I do is honeybee research.
إذن فإن ما أفعله هو أبحاث عن نحل العسل
I got my Ph.D. studying honeybee health.
لقد حصلت على الدكتوراة في دراسة صحة نحل العسل
I started in 2005 studying honeybees.
بدأت في 2005 دراسة نحل العسل
In 2006, honeybees started disappearing,
في 2006 ، بدأ نحل العسل في الاختفاء
so suddenly, like, this little nerd kid
وفجأة ، وكطفل عبقري مهووس
going to school working with bugs — (Laughter) —
يذهب للمدرسة ويعمل مع الحشرات - (ضحك)
became very relevant in the world.
أصبحت مهما في العالم.
And it worked out that way.
وهذا ما يتم بالفعل بنفس الطريقة
So my research focuses on ways to make bees healthier.
لذا فأبحاثي تركز على الوسائل التي تجعل النحل أكثر صحة
I don't research what's killing the bees, per se.
لم تكن أبحاثي عمّ يقتل النحل بالضبط
I'm not one of the many researchers around the world
لست أحد هؤلاء الباحثين الكثر حول العالم
who's looking at the effects of pesticides or diseases
الذين يبحثون في تأثيرات المبيدات الحشرية أو الأمراض
or habitat loss and poor nutrition on bees.
أو فقدان المأوى وسوء التغذية على النحل
We're looking at ways to make bees healthier
نحن نبحث عن الطرق التي تجعل النحل أكثر صحة
through vaccines, through yogurt, like probiotics,
من خلال التطعيمات ، من خلال الزبادي ، مثل المحفزات الحيوية
and other types of therapies in ways that can be fed orally to bees,
وأنواع أخرى من العلاجات التي من الممكن إعطائها للنحل خارجياً
and this process is so easy, even a 7-year-old can do it.
وهذه العملية سهلة جدا، حتى أن الطفل ذو السبع سنوات يستطيع عملها
You just mix up some pollen, sugar and water,
فقط امزج بعض حبوب اللقاح والسكر والماء
and whatever active ingredient you want to put in,
وأي مكون نشط ترغب فيه وضعه
and you just give it right to the bees. No chemicals involved,
وفوراً أعطه للنحل . غير متضمن للكيماويات
just immune boosters.
فقط لتقوية المناعة
Humans think about our own health in a prospective way.
البشر ينظرون إلى صحتنا بطريقة تتطلع إلى المستقبل
We exercise, we eat healthy, we take vitamins.
نقوم بعمل التمرينات ، نأكل طعاماً صحياً ، ونتعاطى الفيتامينات
Why don't we think about honeybees in that same type of way?
لماذا لا ننظر إلى نحل العسل بنفس الطريقة
Bring them to areas where they're thriving
نحضرهم إلى حيث يزدهرون
and try to make them healthier before they get sick.
ونحاول أن نجعلهم أكثر صحة قبل أن يصابوا بالأمراض
I spent many years in grad school trying to poke bees and do vaccines
لقد أمضيت سنوات عديدة في دراساتي العليا أحاول وخز النحل وإعطائهم لقاحات
with needles. (Laughter) Like, years,
بالإبر. (ضحك) لأعوام
years at the bench, "Oh my gosh, it's 3 a.m.
سنوات في مقعد ، "يا إلهي، إنها الثالثة صباحاً"
and I'm still pricking bees." (Laughter)
"وما زلت أوخز النحل " ( ضحك)
And then one day I said, "Why don't we just do an oral vaccine?"
وفي أحد الأيام قلت " لماذا لا نعطيها لقاحا من الخارج؟"
It's like, "Ugh," so that's what we do. (Laughter)
إنه مثل ،"مقرف" إذن هذا ما نفعله . ( ضحك)
I'd love to share with you some images of urban beehives,
أحب أن أشارككم بعض صور خلايا النحل الحضرية
because they can be anything.
لأنها يمكن أن تكون أي شيء
I mean, really open your mind with this.
أعني ، فعلاً افتحوا عقولكم لذلك
You can paint a hive to match your home.
يمكنكم رسم خلية لتلائم منزلكم
You can hide a hive inside your home.
يمكنكم إخفاء خلية داخل منزلكم
These are three hives on the rooftop
هذه ثلاث خلايا فوق سطح
of the Fairmont Copley Plaza Hotel,
فندق فيرمونت كوبلي بلازا
and they're beautiful here. I mean, we matched
وهي جميلة هنا. أعني ، لقد طابقنا
the new color of the inside of their rooms to do
اللون الداخلي الجديد لغرفهم لعمل
some type of a stained wood with blue for their sheets,
نوع من الخشب المبقع بالأزرق لملاءتها
and these bees are terrific, and they also will use
وهذا النحل رائع ، كما سيستخدمون
herbs that are growing in the garden.
الأعشاب التي تنمو في الحديقة
That's what the chefs go to to use for their cooking,
التي يستخدمها الطباخون في أكلاتهم
and the honey -- they do live events --
والعسل -- ينظمون حفلات مباشرة --
they'll use that honey at their bars.
سيستخدمون ذلك العسل في حاناتهم.
Honey is a great nutritional substitute for regular sugar
العسل بديل طبيعي عظيم للسكر العادي
because there are different types of sugars in there.
لأن هناك أنواع مختلفة من السكر
We also have a classroom hives project,
لدينا أيضاً مشروع فصل الخلايا المدرسي
where -- this is a nonprofit venture --
حيث -- هذه جهة غير ربحية --
we're spreading the word around the world for how
نحن ننشر الفكرة حول العالم عن كيفية
honeybee hives can be taken into the classroom
وضع خلايا نحل العسل في الفصل المدرسي
or into the museum setting, behind glass,
أو داخل مواقع المتاحف ، خلف الزجاج
and used as an educational tool.
وتستخدم كأداة تعليمية
This hive that you see here has been
هذه الخلية التي ترونها هنا قد تم وضعها
in Fenway High School for many years now.
في مدرسة فينواي الثانوية لأعوام عدة
The bees fly right into the outfield of Fenway Park.
يطير النحل مباشرة إلى الفناء الخارجي لمتنزه فينواي
Nobody notices it. If you're not a flower,
لم يلحظه أحد. لو لم تكن زهرة
these bees do not care about you. (Laughter)
هذا النحل لايعيرك أي اهتمام ( ضحك)
They don't. They don't. They'll say,
لايفعلون. لا يفعلون. سيقولون
"S'cuse me, flying around." (Laughter)
زز من فضلك ، ويطيرون " ( ضحك)
Some other images here in telling a part of the story
بعض الصور الأخرى هنا تروي لنا جزء من القصة
that really made urban beekeeping terrific is
التي تجعل التربية الحضرية للنحل رائعة
in New York City, beekeeping was illegal until 2010.
في مدينة نيويورك ، تربية النحل كانت غير قانونية حتى 2010
That's a big problem, because what's going to pollinate
إنها مشكلة كبيرة ، ما الذي سيحدث للتلقيح
all of the gardens and the produce locally? Hands?
لكل الحدائق هل تنتج محلياً؟ يدوياً؟
I mean, locally in Boston, there is a terrific company
أعني ، محلياً في بوسطن، هناك شركة رائعة
called Green City Growers, and they are going
تدعى مزارعي المدينة الخضراء ، و سيذهبون
and pollinating their squash crops by hand with Q-Tips,
ويلقحون محاصيلهم باليد بواسطة إبر
and if they miss that three day window, there's no fruit.
ولو فاتهم ذلك لمدة ثلاثة أيام لن يكون هناك ثمار
Their clients aren't happy, and people go hungry.
لم يكن عملاؤهم سعداء وسيجوع شعبهم
So this is important.
لذلك فهذا مهم
We have also some images of honey from Brooklyn.
لدينا كذلك بعض الصور عن العسل من بروكلين
Now, this was a mystery in the New York Times
الآن ، كان ذلك غامضاً في النيويورك تايمز
where the honey was very red, and the
حيث كان العسل محمراً جداً
New York State forensics department came in
جاءت وحدة التحقيقات في نيويورك
and they actually did some science to match
وقاموا ببعض العلوم لمطابقة
the red dye with that found
الصبغة الحمراء الموجودة
in a maraschino cherry factory down the street. (Laughter)
في مصنع الكرز في نهاية الشارع (ضحك).
So you can tailor your honey to taste however you want
إذاً يمكنك صنع العسل ليكون مذاقه كما تشتهي
by planting bee-friendly flowers.
بزراعة أزهار صديقة للنحل
Paris has been a terrific model for urban beekeeping.
أضحت مدينة باريس نموذجا رائعاً في الحفاظ على النحل
They've had hives on the rooftop of their opera house
لديهم خلايا على أسطح دور الأوبرا
for many years now, and that's what really got people started, thinking,
لعدد من السنين الآن، وذلك ما جعل الناس يفكرون،
"Wow, we can do this, and we should do this."
" وااو، يمكننا فعل هذا، وينبغي أن نفعل هذا."
Also in London, and in Europe across the board,
كذلك في لندن، وفي أوروبا عبر الحدود،
they're very advanced in their use of green rooftops
هم متقدمون جداً في استخدام أسطح منازلهم الخضراء
and integrating beehives,
واحتضان خلايا النحل،
and I'll show you an ending note here.
وسأطلعكم على نقطة ختامية هنا
I would like to encourage you to open your mind.
أريد أن أحثكم على فتح اذهانكم
What can you do to save the bees or to help them
ماذا تستطيعون فعله للحفاظ على النحل ومساعدتهم
or to think of sustainable cities in the future?
أو لنفكر باستدامة المدن في المستقبل؟
Well, really, just change your perspective.
حسناً، فقط غيروا من نظرتكم.
Try to understand that bees are very important.
حاولوا فهم أن النحل مهم للغاية.
A bee isn't going to sting you if you see it.
وأن النحلة لن تقوم بلدغك بمجرد رؤيتك لها.
The bee dies. Honeybees die when they sting,
النحل يموت. نحل العسل يموت حينما يلدغ،
so they don't want to do it either. (Laughter)
لذا فهم لا يريدون فعل ذلك. (ضحك)
It's nothing to panic about. They're all over the city.
لا شيء لنفزع منه. النحل موجود في كل المدينة.
You could even get your own hive if you want.
بامكانكم اقتناء خليتكم الخاصة اذا شئتم.
There are great resources available,
هناك موارد عظيمة متاحة،
and there are even companies that will help get you set up and mentor you
وهناك شركات ستساعدكم وتعين لكم مرشدا
and it's important for our educational system in the world
ومن المهم لنظامنا التعليمي في العالم
for students to learn about agriculture worldwide
حتى يتعلم الطلاب حول الزراعة في كل العالم
such as this little girl, who, again, is not even getting stung.
مثل هذه البنت الصغيرة، التي، ومجدداً لم تُلسع حتى.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم.(تصفيق)